Okay, so in this video then we
are going to cover some basic
calculations using EMV, right,
using expected monetary value.
Now EMV then remember is this formula
here, right?
It's probability times impact, your dollar
impact, or whatever
monetary value you're using.
In the exam they will always give you
probability, they will
always give you impact.
You're just multiplying two numbers
together to get your EMV.
So the actual math is very
straightforward.
Because like I said, they give you both
numbers.
Multiply them together, you get your EMV.
Nice and simple.
So a very simple example, then.
Let's say we've identified a risk,
risk one.
Whatever risk one
is, if identified this risk,
there's a 20% probability
of that risk occurring.
We've identified as 20% probability.
As I said, in the exam, they'll always
give you that value.
In reality, you're
going to utilize subject
matter experts, to
come up with that value.
You're going to be using historical
information.
There's many different ways how you'd come
up with that in reality.
For the exam purposes, they will always
give you that value.
So risk one then, there's 20% probability.
If it occurs, there might be a $10,000
impact on our project, right?
Negative value.
Negative number might be a $10,000
negative impact on our project.
So there's a 20% chance that material
prices might increase.
by a certain amount.
We have to use all of these materials.
So we calculate if the
material prices increases by this
amount, then we'll end up
spending an additional $10,000.
So the EMV simply multiply them together,
20% of negative 10,000, negative $2,000.
That's how we EMV expected monetary value.
Talk about another risk here.
Let's say we've identified another risk,
risk two, wherever that risk is.
There's a 30% probability of that risk
occurring.
And if it occurs, we'll end up spending an
additional $3,000, right?
Or we may make $3,000 worth of losses,
or there may be $3,000 worth of damages.
There's a 30% chance that there might be a
flood, for example.
A 30% chance that there's a, you know,
a risk of flood.
We've got heavy rain, it might flood.
And if there's, if that's
a case, then it might
cause $3,000 worth of
damages to our equipment.
So our EMV then, 30% of negative $3,000 is
$900, negative.
Negative $900.
Now notice risk three here is a positive
risk.
It's an opportunity.
There's a 10% chance
we might end up saving
$5,000 or we might end up making $5,000.
So it might be a 10% chance that we may
finish this project early.
This product can go out, you know,
we can sell this product earlier.
We can go out to the market earlier.
We can end up saving or making a an
additional $5,000, right?
Or there's a 10% chance that material
prices might come down.
If they come down, we may
end up saving $5,000 in our
project, in which case in
our EMV is a positive $500.
If they ever ask you
for your total EMV, you
just literally just add up these numbers.
Add up the EMVs, and in this case,
a total EMV negative 2,400.
it.
So the actual calculation is very,
very straightforward.
In the exam, like I said,
they will always give
you probability, they will
always give you impact.
You're just multiplying the two numbers
together to get your EMV.
Now, although they will always give you
those two numbers together, what they will
not do is give you a very nice,
organized little table like this.
What they will do is they'll give you a
paragraph and these numbers will all be
jumbled up in this paragraph they'll give
you a scenario right there's these numbers
will all be jumbled up in the scenario
right so the scenario might say something
like you know you've identified that the
20% chance that there might be an increase
in material prices and there's a 30%
chance that there might be a risk of flood
right if material prices increases you'll
end up spending an additional $10,000 but
then if there's a risk of flood right if
there's a flood then you may end up
spending an additional 3,000 might cost
$3,000 worth of damages
and so and so forth.
So they'll give you a paragraph,
and all these numbers will be jumbled up,
will be mixed in in the paragraph.
There might even be one or two irrelevant
numbers in there as well.
So the numbers will be there.
These numbers will be there.
It's just a case of organizing.
As was most of the questions on the exam,
or rather most of the math questions on
the exam, the actual calculations are
usually quite straightforward.
It's just understanding what numbers you
need and organizing all of those numbers.
Now, now that we've got this $2,400,
this EMV, what do we do with that?
Well, we could use this money to make some
adjustments to our contingency reserve.
So remember, contingency reserves are for
known risks, risks that you have
identified, you meaning the project
manager.
So this is one of the ways
then of putting money aside
or making adjustments
to our contingency reserve.
Now, the other thing I want
to mention here is that this
calculation only works in a
risk-neutral position, right?
When you completely have a risk-neutral
position.
Generally, in reality,
this is not necessarily,
you know, going to work, all right?
You don't necessarily use these
calculations in reality.
This is purely and simply if you have a
purely risk-neutral position.
And what risk-neutral
position means, right,
neither risk-averse, neither risk-seeking.
Essentially what it's saying is,
as these percentages increases,
then these EMV is going
to increase, and so you're
going to put more money
in contingency reserve.
Right now, there's a 20%
chance that, you know,
you may end up spending
an additional $10,000.
However, if that risk
materializes, you are on
the hook for the entire
$10,000, not just a 20%.
So the whole principle behind this,
then, as this probability increases,
then the EMV increases, and so you put
more money in contingency reserve.
So once this goes to 30%, that
EMV is, you know, $3,000 now,
and so you're going to put more
money in contingency reserve.
And when that goes to 40%, the EMV
increases now, to $4,000.
So you put more money in contingency
reserve.
Now, in most cases, most organizations and
most people are going to have some kind of
cut off between when we consider it a risk
and when we actually consider it an issue.
Right.
So as a simple example, right,
if you're living in the Midwest,
Midwest of the US or northern
part of the US and you're in
winter and they tell you there's
a 80% chance of a snowstorm.
Well, you don't think, well, there's a 20%
chance it might.
not happen.
If there's an 80% chance of a snowstorm,
then you just assume that there's going to
be a snowstorm if you're
living pretty much anywhere
in the Midwest or in the
northern part of the US.
But if you had a risk-neutral position,
then that is what you would think.
You think, well, there's a 20% chance it
might not happen.
So usually there's going to be some kind
of cut-off where you don't consider it,
I'm talking about in reality, where you
don't consider it a risk anymore,
you don't consider it
in uncertainty, you're
going to now deal with
it as though it's an issue.
Right.
So as another simple example,
let's say this activity may
cause some physical danger,
physical harm to our team members.
There's a 20% chance that our team members
may be physically injured.
Well, we're not going
to turn around and think,
well, there's an 80%
chance it might not happen.
No, if we figure that there's a 20% chance
that, you know, our team members may get
physically injured by
performing this activity,
we're going to do
something about it right now.
to us, that's not going to be a risk
anymore.
Now, we're going to deal with that as an
issue.
And so that's the reason why this is not
necessarily going to work in reality,
but this is a kind of question,
though, that you could get on the exam.
So, like I said, on the
exam, they'll always give
you probability, they will
always give you impact.
Multiply the two numbers together, and you
get your EMV, your
expected monetary value.